<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The primitive cavalerism revived, or, A recognition of the principles of the old cavaleers published on occasion of some late pamphlets and papers, reviving and justifying the pretentions of the long Parliament, begun in 1641 / by an old loyal cavaleer.</title>
            <author>Old loyal cavaleer.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55871</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3468</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3036</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11951380</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11951380</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51428</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55871)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51428)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 820:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The primitive cavalerism revived, or, A recognition of the principles of the old cavaleers published on occasion of some late pamphlets and papers, reviving and justifying the pretentions of the long Parliament, begun in 1641 / by an old loyal cavaleer.</title>
                  <author>Old loyal cavaleer.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Croom ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>In support of Charles I.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51428:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Primitive Cavaleriſm REVIVED: OR A RECOGNITION OF THE PRINCIPLES OF THE OLD CAVALEERS. Publiſhed on occaſion of ſome late <hi>PAMPHLETS</hi> and <hi>PAPERS,</hi> Reviving and Juſtifying the Pretentions of the Long Parliament, Begun in 1641. <hi>By an Old Loyal Cavaleer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed By <hi>George Croom,</hi> at the <hi>Blew-Ball</hi> in <hi>Thames-ſtreet,</hi> over againſt <hi>Baynard</hi>'s <hi>Caſtle,</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:51428:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51428:2"/>
            <head>THE Primitive Cavaleriſm REVIVED: OR A RECOGNITION OF THE PRINCIPLES OF THE OLD CAVALEERS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN the unhappy quarrel betwixt King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt of Bleſſed Memory and the two Houſes of Parliament broke out, I thought my ſelf obliged for the conduct of my own Conſcience to endeavor to underſtand clearly the grounds, which each ſide inſiſted on for their own Vindication; And having obſerved of late ſome Papers and Pamphlets to be diſperſed abroad, containing the principles by which that long Parliament did ſeek to juſtifie their taking up Arms againſt his Sacred Majeſty; I have endeavoured to refute them by contrapoſition of the principles of the Old Loyal Cavaleers; Leſt thoſe State-hereſys ſhould be imbibed again by ſome of the people, to the prejudice of the publick Peace.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore, We Royaliſts judged, that the people were not the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal of Government, and that it was little leſs than blaſphemy to aſſert it, ſeeing God himſelf hath aſſerted in Scripture (<hi>Ro.</hi> 13.1. and otherwhere) that Government is his Ordinance. Nor did we judge Government to be his Ordinance ſingly on the account of his revelation of his will in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but that as the other parts of the Moral Law are ſeminally contained in that, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or inward dignoſcitive power of mans Souls, by which he hath a natural, diſtinctive ſenſe of what is juſt or unjuſt, comely or uncomely, ſo was alſo that Principle (at Firſt Aeconomical, afterwards Political) That
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51428:3"/>men ought to Honour their Parents and to obey them injoining things juſt and comely, or ſubmit to them puniſhing them for the contrary.</p>
            <p>For ſeeing God brought none into the World <hi>Independant</hi> from Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitors, ſaving the firſt Man and Woman, and of that one blood made all the Nations of Men to dwell upon the face of the Earth, <hi>Acts.</hi> 17.26. Reaſon tells men, they are to obey their Progenitors who are inſtrumental under God to give being and birth to them and their brethren, in all things injoyned by them, as which are juſt and comely, and conducing to the common good of the Family (for reaſon tells us alſo that it is juſt to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the common good before that of a private or particular Member.) It is true where the things required by the Progenitor did <hi>bona fide</hi> appear to the conſcience of the Deſcendent, to be a ſin, the Deſcendent was bound to obey God the Supreme Lawgiver rather than Man; but in bare prudentials and expedients for the common good, no Deſcendent had a right to vie judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and diſcretion with his Superior, tho he might humbly advertiſe his Superior of the inexpediency of the thing required as he judged.</p>
            <p>From hence it follows (as reaſonable to be ſuppoſed) that God had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſited in the Progenitor a power to compel his Deſcendents to do juſt and comely things, and things conducing to the Common intereſt of the family.</p>
            <p>And tho a Progenitor might wilfully or ignorantly abuſe his power, enjoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing things unjuſt or detrimental to the publick good of the Family, yet was his perſon to be ſacred and inviolable, and he was not to be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by way of ſuffering (as formal Adminiſtration) to his Deſcendents, nor was he to be reſiſted by them by force; for reaſon tells us, that to reſerve ſuch a liberty in the Inferiors, to reſiſt or animadvert on their Progenitor, gives a Licence to any Rebellious perſon, and furniſheth him with a pretence to overthrow all, both <hi>Domeſtick</hi> and <hi>Civil</hi> Societys, by pretending a violation of Juſtice and Equity, or a detrimenting of the publick good by the Superior. The Apoſtle therefore may well be ſuppoſed to expound the common ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Mankind in what they thought comely and juſt towards Progenitors, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.9, 10. <hi>Though the Fathers of our fleſh corrected us</hi> (according to their own pleaſure or paſſions many times) yet we gave them reverence and thought our ſelves obliged ſo to do. This therefore being a fixed Principle to us, that the Patriark, or Father of the Family was by Gods appointment Supreme Governour over his Family, we thought our ſelves Warranted to make theſe deductions from it:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That where a Deſcendent committed wickedneſs, there not only his immediate Father, but alſo this Grand-Father, or great Grand-Father (and ſo upwards in the right aſcendent Line) might and ought (if the Father was either Dead or negligent) to inflict puniſhment on him. And we have if not an inſtance, yet an intimation of this in holy Scripture, <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.45. Where <hi>Rebekah</hi> adviſeth <hi>Jacob</hi> to fly from the Murderus deſign of his Brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> (who had reſolved to kill him after his Father <hi>Iſaacs</hi> Death) which <hi>Eſau,</hi> v. 41. thought to be at hand, <hi>Why, ſaith ſhe, ſhould I alſo be deprived of you both in one day?</hi> Which intimates there was ſome Anceſtors alive who might judge <hi>Eſau</hi> for Fratricide tho <hi>Iſaac</hi> was dead.</p>
            <p>And ſo indeed the Sacred Chronology aſſures us there was, at the time of <hi>Eſaus</hi> threatning <hi>Jacob,</hi> for <hi>Shem,</hi> died not till the year of the World. 2158. And <hi>Eſau</hi> is ſuppoſed by Chronologers to have Married his <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitiſh</hi> Wives. 214. (who probably might inſtigate him to revenge)
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51428:3"/>Ten years before <hi>Shems,</hi> Death. And <hi>Heber</hi> died not till the year of the World 2187. Which was long after <hi>Jacobs</hi> fleeing into <hi>Meſopotamia.</hi> So that tho <hi>Iſaac</hi> did not really die till 2228. Yet <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Rebekah,</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing he might have died ſooner, ſhe concludes that one of the ſurviving Anceſtors might and ought to have executed Vengeance on <hi>Eſau,</hi> for <hi>Fratri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide,</hi> the like inference may be made from the Parable of the Widdow wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>Tekoah,</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.6, 7.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſecond inference is, That Women tranſlated out of their Fathers Family by Marriage (<hi>forisfamiliatae,</hi> as the Civilians ſpeak) were ſubjected to the Juriſdiction of the Father of the Family into which they were Married, thus <hi>Judah,</hi> doomed <hi>Tamar,</hi> his Daughter in Law, to the Fire for ſuppoſed Adultery, <hi>Gen.</hi> 38.24.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A Third inference very probably deduced from the former Principle is, That the Father or Patriark Dying the Regal power deſcended on the Eldeſt Son, who was to Rule over the Family, even over his Brethren, ſo long as they continued to reſide in the Society of the Clan, and claimed the Protection of that Society, and did not tranſmigrate to make a new Colony. We have an inſtance in Scripture which ſeems to be of this ſignificancy, namely, when <hi>Abraham took Lot his Brother Harans Son, and carried him with him into Canaan, Gen.</hi> 12.5. Which looks more like an Exerciſe of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority than of truſt; and that thus it is amongſt the Clans of ſome Indians is reported by Travellors. And there are ſome Footſteps of it amongſt the Clans of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> and <hi>Highlanders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The Fourth Inference is this, That ſeeing no Man (<hi>Adam,</hi> the firſt only excepted) came into the World in a ſtate of <hi>Independent</hi> Liberty free from Government, but was ſubject to his Parents, therefore no man was born in a ſtate of War, but in a Political ſubjection according to the Fifth Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Honour thy Father,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>All this of Patriarchal Juriſdiction I collect from the ſacred ſtory after the Flood, for before the Flood <hi>Cains</hi> eſcaping puniſhment from <hi>Adam,</hi> for <hi>Abels</hi> Murder, in all probability incouraged his Offspring the Giants and other men of Renown, to ſhake off all Patriarchal Government, and fill the Earth with violence, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.11. So that want of the exerciſe of the Patriarchal Government was one meritorious cauſe of the bringing the Flood upon the Old World. The like defect ruined <hi>Elies</hi> family. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.13.</p>
            <p>But to return to our Principle, and give ſome reaſons why we <hi>Cavalcers</hi> believed the Original of Government thus to be from God, not from the People;</p>
            <p>Firſt, No man hath a right to diſpoſe of his own Life to the pleaſure of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other: only God the Author of Being could give a Power to the Progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, (the inſtrument of the being of his Deſcendents) to diſpoſe of the Life of an offending Deſcendent in the proſecution of Juſtice, according to <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.6. <hi>Whoſoever ſheddeth mans Blood by man ſhall his Blood be ſhed.</hi> So that if the people were the Original of Government the Magiſtrate had been a Murderer in executing Vengeance even on a Murderer; And the Murderer had been <hi>Felo de ſe,</hi> a ſelf Murderer in ſubmitting to the Sentence.</p>
            <p>Secondly We believed Government to be from God, becauſe the Laws made by Governours were generally for the incouragement of Vertue and Piety and for the ſuppreſſion of Vice, ſo that the fruit ſhewed that Government was a Plant of our heavenly Fathers planting, whereas people being generally
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51428:4"/>Wicked, would, if they had been the original of Government, have ſet up ſuch Governours as ſhould have Eſtabliſhed iniquity by a Law.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Add, That that Spirit of Government poured out upon Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours ſhewed, that God who alone can ſo indow them doth commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate them as his Vicegerents. Therefore it is ſaid, <hi>Pro.</hi> 16.10. <hi>A di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſentence, or a judgment from God is in the lips of the King:</hi> And the eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial wiſdom of God, ſaith <hi>Pro.</hi> 8.15. <hi>By me Kings Reign, and Princes decree Juſtice.</hi> The art of Government or King-craft is from the Lord.</p>
            <p>Fourthly It is obſerved in all Hiſtory, that Rebells were ordinarily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed with divine Vengeance: But we <hi>Cavaleers,</hi> could not think that God would ingage his Power and Juſtice to vindicate an Idol of the peoples ſetting up.</p>
            <p>So that Fifthly, Had not God ſaid of Magiſtrates, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.6. <hi>I have ſaid ye are Gods,</hi> obedience in the people to them had been Idolatry, in ſetting up a Creature of their own as a God, and worſhipping it.</p>
            <p>Sixthly But our chief reaſon was, becauſe Scripture ſo peremptorily aſſerts it, <hi>Ro.</hi> 13.1. <hi>That Magiſtrates are Gods Miniſters, and Gods Ordinance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this firſt Poſition was thus eſtabliſhed to us, That God and not the people, was the Original of Government, we proceeded to inquire, how the Patriarchal Government over ſingle Clans or Familys and the Deſcendents in them, paſſed into a more ample Government over many diſtinct Familys (before independent from one another) And we thought it reaſonable to conclude, that this change came into the World either by a forced or vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary Compact.</p>
            <p>A forced compact was, when the King or Patriark of one Family or Clan overcame the Patriark of another Family, and his Family, and forced them to conſent to obey him, as did thoſe of his own Family, or, it may be, he impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed worſe conditions of Servitude, Tranſportation, Tribute or other hardſhips upon them, as the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Monarchs did, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.32. And ſo doth the <hi>Turk</hi> at this day, ſetting the conquered under his Timuriots. But in this caſe of Conqueſt two things are obſervable: Namely firſt, That the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering Patriark might happen to abate ſomething of his own Dominion over his own Clan, on account of his own Wars againſt the other Family, having before the expedition promiſed his own Subjects and their Poſterity ſome Immunities if they would be Faithful and Courageous. And probably many of the Immunitys which Subjects claim, own their riſe to ſuch promiſes, which being once made they ought to be obſerved by the Prince or Patriark, Thus King <hi>Saul</hi> promiſed, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.25. That whoſoever would combat and kill <hi>Goliah,</hi> he would inrich him, and make his Fathers houſe free in <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, it is undeniable, that Conqueſt in it ſelf is no obligation to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to the Conquerour, for no man can pretend by Conqueſt a right to ſeize my Liberty and to abridge my Allegiance to my Natural Prince, but I can more juſtly pretend my right (when ever I am able) to recover my Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and free Exerciſe of Allegiance to my natural Leige Lord; So that till compact confirm Conqueſt, ſubmiſſion to the Conquerour is only a taking Quarter, which implys, I will do nothing againſt the Life of him that gives me Quarter, till by redemption or reprizal (by my Prince or his Allys) I recover my liberty. Only therefore Compact after Conqueſt can lay an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to Subjection to the Conquerour, and how long it is before ſuch a Compact becomes Valid and obliging, whilſt our natural Prince continues in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51428:4"/>Arms and yields not, is ſomething difficult to determine, for my part I think that for ſo long it is not a valid compact, but only a taking Quarter.</p>
            <p>But tho Conqueſt, and the Compacts iſſuing upon them, was the ordinary way of imbodying many Familys under one Governour yet undoubtedly voluntary Compacts alſo did the ſame in many times and places, many Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arks and their Clans Aſſociating together for mutual defence againſt potent Enemys, and ſubjecting themſelves to ſome one Patriark or famous man amongſt them, who was to go in and out before them, and Fight their Battels: Thus the <hi>Gileadites</hi> choſe <hi>Jephtah</hi> and the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> deſired in <hi>Samuels</hi> time ſuch a King, and obtained <hi>Saul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then we are to obſerve that thoſe Compacts were chiefly, if not only, ratified by the conſent of the Patriarks combining; So that the inferior mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Familys had little or no Vote in the making the Compact, and the ſetting the conditions of it. So that the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> who aſſembled for <hi>Sauls</hi> election and inauguration, were the Elders of the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.4. Theſe voluntary Compacts between Patriarks were ſometimes with Reſervation of a ſhare in the Government, amongſt all the Patriarks, one only preſiding in Council, ſo that the Major Vote was to over-rule for the making municipal Laws, and War, or Leagues with Foraigners, and for ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing Officers Military or Civil, and this is properly an Ariſtocratical Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, or States.</p>
            <p>When the Compacts of the combining Patriarks carried over all their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty to ſome one perſon, whom they choſe to preſide over them only perſonally, during his Life, this was an Elective Kingdom; when they devol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it on any one Patriark and his Succeſſors, this was alſo an elective Kingdom in the origination of it, but became in proceſs and Succeſſion, an Hereditary Monarchy or Kingdom: And ſuch are moſt of the Kingdoms of the World at this day.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Democracy</hi> wherein the whole body of the People, meeting in their <hi>Comitial</hi> or General Aſſemblys did make <hi>Plebiſcita</hi> or popular Decrees, it is hard for me to gueſs how Patriarchal power ever came to be ſo ravilled out into that form, unleſs the Multitude forced their Patriarks to yield them a ſhare in the Government, either by Tumults or Seceſſions, and departing from their No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles or <hi>Patricii,</hi> of which there are many inſtances in the <hi>Roman Common-Wealth,</hi> for that any People whether the heads of ſeveral Familys, or the whole body of the People ſhould only conditionally intruſt the Government in the hands of a Soveraign or a Senate, with power of revocation of their truſt upon Male-adminiſtration, is ſuch an unpolitical phancy as deſerves to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploded by all who wiſh well to the Peace of the World, and of the Nations in it, for ſuch a conſtitution carrys ſelf-deſtroying principles in it, ſeeing every ambitious or diſcontented perſon making himſelf Popular might eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the multitude (who are generally prone to Change, and Querulous againſt their Governors) that their Superiors had forfeited their truſt and they might reſume their Power betruſted, and commit it into better hands.</p>
            <p>And to be ſure when an Army was on Foot, whoſe Commanders were prompted by their intereſt in the Soldiery to aſpire, this pretence would be ready at hand, that the Soveraign or the Senate had failed in their truſt, and that the People might reaſſume the Government, and withal, that <hi>Populus Armatus is eſt Populus,</hi> that thoſe who had the Arms of the Nation in their hands were the People.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:51428:5"/>
            <p>This was the very Plea which the Phanatick Army under <hi>Cromwel,</hi> did make, and it pleaſed us Old <hi>Cavaleers</hi> well, when we ſaw <hi>Cromwel,</hi> turn the point of this Principle upon his Maſters, and turn the <hi>Rump</hi> out of doors, alledging, and with truth enough, that they had failed in the truſt repoſed in them by the good People of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the ſame account we Old <hi>Cavaleers,</hi> deteſted as unpolitical, and laying the Foundation for perpetual civil jars, the ſwearing of Allegiance to the Supream Power with limitation; as it was in that called the <hi>Solemn-League</hi> and <hi>Covenant,</hi> Pagragraph the 2d, wherein they promiſed to preſerve the Kings Perſon and Authority in the preſervation of the true Religion and Libertys of the Kingdoms. When therefore the <hi>Scotch</hi> Commiſſioners Pleaded their Engagement by Covenant to appear againſt the Execrable Murdering of our late Soveraign the Royal Martyr, I well remember that the <hi>Rump,</hi> in their Declaration and anſwer to the Papers of the <hi>Scotch</hi> Commiſſioners, Pleaded that the Covenant only obliged them to endeavor the Preſervation of the Kings Perſon in the Preſervation of the true Religion, and the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tys of the Kingdoms, and that in limited Propoſitions <hi>Limitatio eſt pars potior,</hi> the Limitation is the predominant part. And that therefore ſeeing it was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent to them, that the King had violated the true Religion and the Libertys of the Kingdoms, they (who had taken the Covenant as well as the <hi>Scots</hi>) looked on themſelves as obliged by Covenant to depoſe the King and bring him to condign Puniſhment.</p>
            <p>But our Contemplations in proſecution of this Subject about the Original and exerciſe of Power ran yet on further, for we obſerved that there were two parts of the Patriarchal Governing Power appointed by God, namely the Legiſlative Power, to enact wholſom conſtitutions for the good of the Clan or Family (<hi>He is the Miniſter of God to us for good, Rom.</hi> 13.)</p>
            <p>And the executive Power to put thoſe Laws in Execution, as alſo to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell his Deſcendents to obey the Divine Laws, both Moral and Poſitive, and this alſo was part of the executive Power. For where human Powers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand what God hath commanded before, their Laws are not conſtitutive, but only declarative of the duty, only they may be conſtitutive of the Penalty and Sanction. Both theſe Powers the Legiſlative and executive (under which is comprized the Power to Levy moneys, <hi>for this cauſe pay you Tribute, Rom.</hi> 13.) were intirely in every Patriark.</p>
            <p>But when many Patriarchates or Clans were imbodied into a larger Rega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity or Kingdom by voluntary compact, it is eaſy to conceive that theſe Powers might be diverſly betruſted: And the former (the Legiſlative Power) might only be intruſted to the elected King and his Succeſſors, in concomitancy with the other Patriarks. But ſtill we are to obſerve, that if the Elected King and his Succeſſors had only a Vote, in the making Laws, with the other Patriarks, ſo that the Majority of Votes over ruled, againſt his Vote, then tho he had the name King, he was indeed no King, nor Supreme Governour, but only the chief Magiſtrate, ſuch were the Kings of <hi>Sparta;</hi> the <hi>Lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demonian</hi> Government therefore is reckoned truly an <hi>Ariſtocracy</hi> or <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracy.</hi> But ſome Nations might perhaps find out a better way, namely, that the Legiſlative Power was betruſted to the elected Patriark and his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, yet ſo that it ſhould not be exerted without the conſent of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bining Patriarks, but ſtill the Legiſlative was ſo in the King, that the Votes of all the combining Patriarks could not conſtitute Law without a <hi>Le Roy Le
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51428:5"/>Voult,</hi> the King conſents and commands it to be: And this Government un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly is a Monarchy not deprived of any part of the Power Patriarchal, but only reſtrained in the exerciſe of one part of it, namely, the Legiſlative without the concurrence of others.</p>
            <p>But we obſerved further, that though in a Monarch there might be a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriction of the exerciſe of the Patriarchal, Legiſlative power, there could be none in the exerciſe of the Executive power, for if that could not be exerted but with the conſent of others, ſuch a Nominal King was no Monarch or Supreme Governour, but only the chief Magiſtrats, as we ſaid before. And no man can reaſonably ſuppoſe, that a Patriark who had the plenary power (both Legiſlative and Executive) over his own Clan, and probably was the cheif in puiſſance amongſt the Patriarks combining (as the <hi>Hethites</hi> told <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 23.6. <hi>My Lord thou art a mighty Prince amongſt us</hi>) would ever conſent to abate any thing of his <hi>Regalia</hi> over his own Clan as to the Legiſlative, and ſuffer others to have a reſtraint upon the exerciſe of it, unleſs upon the terms premiſed, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That the exerting his Legiſlative ſhould not indeed be without the Concurence of the other Patriarks, but withal, that all they Voting together ſhould not be able to make a Law without his Royal Authority and conſent; and that alſo the intire, executive Power not only over his own Clan, but even over the Combining Patriarks, and their Clans, ſhould be his, without <hi>Compere</hi> or Coordinate: Thus <hi>Samuel</hi> expounds to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> (amongſt whom God himſelf ſeemed to reſerve the Legiſlative to himſelf, having given them a body of Laws neceſſary to conſerve Peace, or do Juſtice about Inheritances, Injurys Marriages, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) the manner of the King whom they would have to go in and out before them after the manner of other Nations, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.11.</p>
            <p>We find indeed, that in moſt of the Eaſtern Empires, yea and in the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire (after the <hi>Lex Regia</hi> was paſt) both Legiſlative and executive Powers were without reſtraint in the Emperour. And the <hi>Placita Principum,</hi> or <hi>Edicta Imperatoria</hi> were perfect Laws after the promulgation of them. It was a miſtake therefore in him who writ the Life of <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate, to call Chriſtianity the Religion of the Empire, when <hi>Julian</hi> had declared by his Royal Edicts for Paganiſm: And probably ſuch abſolute Monarchys were all which aroſe out of Conqueſt, and Compacts iſſuing from Conqueſt.</p>
            <p>But in many of the Northern Nations (the Offspring of <hi>Japhet,</hi> the Elder) we have reaſon to believe there was a reſtraint upon the Legiſlative till the Nobles <hi>Majorum &amp; Minorum Gentium,</hi> did at leaſt <hi>legem petere &amp; eligere,</hi> requeſt and chuſe, or propoſe a Bill to be enacted a Law.</p>
            <p>And the Power to deny a propoſed Bill, was in the Prince, and the Power to execute Laws wholly in him, and both without Power in the combining Patriarks to call him to account for Adminiſtration of either, or to reaſſume the Power or any part of it, without the Princes Voluntary conſent, theſe ſpeculations about the paſſing of the Patriarchal Monarchy into larger Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments gave us Royaliſts light enough, to diſcover that the pretenſions of the Parliament-Party and the maxims they had eſpouſed were both unpoliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and unpeaceable: Such as thoſe before mentioned; That the People are the original Power, that men are born in a ſtate of <hi>Independent</hi> Liberty, and conſequently in a State of War: That the Power of the Supreme Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour is but a revocable truſt, and he liable to cenſure for Male-admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration. And that the King, tho <hi>ſingulis Major, is univerſis Minor;</hi> for how can he be leſs than all who hath the Power of all concentring in him?</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:51428:6"/>
            <p>Another ſuggeſtion alſo by that ſide in the late times I will here take notice of, tho it lye not in the direct run and way of my Diſcourſe. And it was this, that a Republick or Ariſtocracy was more eligible than a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy. In the manage of which their Writers dealt very deceitfully, for they uſually compared a King miſgoverning, with a Republick Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well, whereas if they had ſtated the compariſon (as of right it ſhould have been) betwixt a King and a <hi>Commonwealth</hi> both Ruling well, or both Ruling ill, it would be moſt evident both from reaſon and Hiſtory (to which adds alſo the experience of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation in the late Confuſions) that leſs evils did ariſe to the People from a King miſgoverning, and gratifying the Luſt of his Minions, than from an Ariſtocracy miſgoverning, and every one of them preying for himſelf and his Dependents, upon the Poor oppreſſed People; and contrarily, that more good comes to a People by the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a wiſe and good King, then by the Government of even wiſe and good <hi>Nobiliſſimo's</hi> (as at <hi>Venice.</hi>)</p>
            <p>But that which eſpecially prevailed upon us <hi>Cavaleers</hi> conſcientiouſly, to ingage for our Soveraign, was the conſideration of the Government under which we were Born. For we knew it from our Fathers, and their Tradition, and from our Old Hiſtorians writing in the Ages paſt; That this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was an hereditary Monarchy immemorially; whence we inferr'd, That all the rights of Monarchy were inherent in our Kings.</p>
            <p>It is true we found the Royal, Legiſlative Authority by Ancient Cuſtom was not put in exerciſe without the conſent of the two Houſes of Parliament: And Cuſtom is Common-Law in <hi>England.</hi> And that thus it was we had no reaſon to be diſpleaſed; nor did we ſollicitouſly inquire into the Original of that uſage whether in the Primitive coalition of the Government the ſeveral Patriarks of <hi>Angels, Jutes</hi> and <hi>Saxons</hi> had ſo compacted with him whom they conſented ſhould be the Univerſal Monarch over them and their Clans, or rather whether our Kings had granted that high Priviledge to our Fathers the Valiant <hi>Angles, Jutes</hi> and <hi>Saxons</hi> to ingage their Valour and fidelity in their warlike expeditions, and after extended the ſame Priviledge in a great meaſure to the <hi>Britains</hi> growing up into one People, with us; or whether any other way this came about we could not tell; thus we found it, and found the Government the beſt tempered Government in the World. And we bleſs God for it, and rejoiced under the ſhadow of it.</p>
            <p>Only this we judged from the preambles of ancient Statutes, and from the Kings Coronation Oath, That the two Houſes did <hi>Legem petere &amp; eligere,</hi> but the King did <hi>Legem ferre &amp; jubere,</hi> the Priviledge of the two Houſes of Parliament was to chuſe and deſire ſuch a Bill to be a Law, and the Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of the King to enact and will it. If herein we were miſtaken, we were miſtaken.</p>
            <p>But be it as it will, we Primitive <hi>Cavaleers</hi> were far from deſigning to remove the Ancient Land-marks which our Fathers had ſet: Nor did we ever think it agreeable to modeſty, for us private Men to ſet bounds to the Power of the Parliament, during its Seſſion, further than that they could do nothing to any Effect without the Royal Aſſent. We believed therefore they could call any Subject to account for ill behaviour in any Office, Military or Civil, by Bill of Attainder or otherwiſe, according to the Uſages of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they could change <hi>Tenures,</hi> put down ſome Courts of Juſtice, erect new ones, and what not? If the King Conſented; and we found that our Kings
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51428:6"/>ſeldom denied the deſires and Requeſts of their Parliaments in matters fit and juſt. But we deteſted the contrivance of ſome Factious Men, who brought the Rout to call for Juſtice againſt the Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi> and Arch-Biſhop <hi>Laud.</hi> And tho there have been oft Factions in Parliaments ſince that unhappy Diſtinction of a Court-Party and a Country-Party, and tho the <hi>Rump</hi> Parliament had caſt us into horrid Confuſions, and robbed us of the beſt of Kings, yet were we not weary of Parliaments, or forward to inſlave our ſelves or our Poſterity: We therefore with thankfulneſs to God above all, and to our good Kings, and Parliaments under them, remembred that Parliaments were the great Conſervers of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Libertys againſt all unjuſt Judges and Officers, and how they oft attempted, even in Popery times, and at laſt Effected the deliverance of the Kingdom and Church of <hi>England</hi> from the Uſurpation of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſecured the People from the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltys of the Bloody Clergy thereof.</p>
            <p>But tho we owned thus, that our Kings had not exerciſed the Legiſlative Power immemorially without the propoſal and conſent of the two Houſes, yet we eaſily diſcovered the cheat of that Parliament comment on the Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical maxim, <hi>Coordinata ſe invicem ſupplent</hi> (tho the proper words are <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinata ſe invicem Complent;</hi>) whence they of that ſide argued, That ſeeing <hi>Coordinates</hi> do mutually ſupply and compleat one another, and that the King withdraw from his Parliament, the two Houſes (whom they judged <hi>Coordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi> with the King in the Legiſlative) might ſupply by an ordinance his abſence or diſſent: which is an inference contrary to all reaſon and ſenſe; for the true ſenſe of that Maxim is this, That <hi>Coordinate,</hi> (ſuppoſe three) do ſo mutually ſupply force to, and compleat on another, that the concurrence of no two of them is Efficacious to the intent for which they are <hi>Coordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate,</hi> without the Concurrence of the third: Thus if we ſhould yield a Coordination as to the Legiſlative Power betwixt the King and two Houſes; yet the Votes of the two Houſes are no Law in <hi>England</hi> without the Royal Aſſent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> It was then uſually objected, That this Doctrine puts the King and either Houſe, into a capacity to hinder a good and wholſom Law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> To this it is anſwered, that the Laws in being are to be ſuppoſed ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient in the Judgment of our Fathers of the laſt Age, to conſerve the State in its being; and whether the Bill propoſed be conducing to the better being of it or no, muſt be ſubmitted to the judgment of the King.</p>
            <p>But ſtill we looked upon the executive Power of Law as wholly and intirely Inherent in our Soveraign without <hi>Compere</hi> or <hi>Coordinate:</hi> who could at his pleaſure derive that Power to others Legally Commiſſioned by him, to put the Laws in Execution. And that therefore the Power of the Militia, of making Judges and Officers, of conferring Honours, of making War, or Peace, or Leagues with Forreiners, was wholly in the King. But if any of the Kings Officers violate our Rights and Priviledges, either Civil or Eccleſiaſtical, which are by Acts of Parliament or Immemorial Cuſtom inſtated on the Subject, the Subject might ſue the violaters in the Kings <hi>Courts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that greater ſecurity for the Rights of any People, I think cannot, by any human Wiſdom be invented, then what we Engliſh-men injoy. For Firſt, we have the protection of the Kings Royal Authority, whoſe inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt it is (ſeeing the Throne is Eſtabliſhed by Juſtice) to make his Officers Peace, and his Exactors Righteouſneſs, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 60.17. Next we have the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51428:7"/>ſecurity of the Laws in being, and of the Reverend and Learned Judges, Commiſſioned for the execution of them; who we may think will be very unwilling to infringe our Rights by Law Eſtabliſhed; both becauſe they are for the ſame accountable at all times to the King, and alſo to a Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament when it ſhall ſit; and likewiſe becauſe they cannot inſlave us by denying us the juſt protection of the Laws, at a cheaper rate then inſlaving their own Poſterity alſo. And laſtly, We have the ſecurity of Parliaments, who cannot only propoſe and enact with the Royal Aſſent new Laws for our future defence againſt unjuſt Officers, but can alſo call them to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for the breach of the Laws already made: this was the Political Creed of the old Cavaleers: and we triumphed in the Victory of Truth, (when any being convinced of the agreeableneſs of our Principles both to Scripture, Reaſon and the Conſtitution we were under) came over and Eſpouſed our cauſe: Thus it appears from what we have ſaid, that we Cavaleers had the better cauſe; but our Sins ruined us and it, and deprived us of the beſt Earthly King in the World, who was Murdered by Bloudy Men; our high provocations drawing God into the quarrel againſt us: Though after he had Scourged us, he was pleaſed in infinite Mercy, and by Miraculous Providence, to make up our breaches in the happy Reſtoration of his Sacred Majeſty who now Reigns; and long may he Reign over us and our Children.</p>
            <closer>GOD SAVE THE KING.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed By <hi>George Croom,</hi> at the <hi>Blew-Ball</hi> in <hi>Thames-ſtreet,</hi> over againſt <hi>Baynard's Caſtle,</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
